What levels of total and free
testosterone do you average see uh when
patients feel good? Oh, that's a good
question. Um, you know, I I would
ballpark a free testosterone for most of
my patients somewhere in the ballpark of
no less than 20 nanogs per deciliter.
Um, probably closer to 40 45 nanogs per
deciliter. Um, so I I I tend to have a
pretty broad range there. Uh I have
found that again I frankly think a lot
of men are significantly underdosed. Um
I know uh Ke Keith uh Nichols has I
think been on here before and spoken to
that well. Uh and I I think he's well
versed in that topic. Um I I do find
that a lot of people have a confusion
when it comes to hormone replacement
therapy.
uh and and I don't know if you know the
best way to put it, but essentially
don't confuse endogenous or internal
hormone production and processing with
hormone replacement therapy. It's not a
onetoone at all. And when you start
playing that game, you can you can end
up in a bad position for your patients.
So, um I do tend to push the
testosterone levels a little bit higher.
Um and I I find that a lot of my
patients do feel best in that slightly
higher range. Uh so just a total for
example would be it's probably something
closer to the ballpark of 900 NOGS per
deciliter. Um and with the creams gosh
it's hard to keep it under 14 or 1500
sometimes. Uh they are really really
potent at pushing those levels up. Yeah
shorting. Um yeah I regularly see for
myself 1 1200 1300 nanogs per deciliter
which is still normal and fine. Um but
still on our lab our lab ranges here in
Europe are a maximum of 900 950 nanogs
per DC liter. So they brought down all
these um yeah lab ranges that's probably
because of an unhealthy population.
Yes. I I couldn't agree more. Yeah. And
what what would be the reason that our
general population is lower in um
leestosterone than generations before?
Um, maybe I think it's a good moment to
start talking about EDCs.
Yeah, I love that. I love this question.
Um, endocrine disrupting chemicals, uh,
is what you're referring to, Stephen.
And and it's fascinating and we're I
think we're really frankly just starting
to learn more about this. Um, so we have
our endocrine disrupting chemicals which
are probably the most prevalent and and
the most potent. Um and and so literally
if you guys can think about it uh these
chemicals look, act and behave very
similarly uh to estrogenic hormones. And
so uh most plastics uh are are probably
probably the most popular thing where
this would be coming from. Uh and in
this day and age, it's almost impossible
to avoid them. I mean actually I would
say it is literally impossible to avoid
them. Uh there are, you know, plastics
in our clothing, there are plastics in
our foods, there are plastics, uh, you
know, in and around us all the time. Um,
and that's not to be pessimistic, but
what we're ending up with is a is a
really dire position where we've lost um
and and Stephen, I don't know what it is
in Europe necessarily, but I think in
the United States, we're down about 50
to 60%
uh in total testosterone since I think
the 60s and 70s. Um, which is massive.
Absolutely insane. uh in a very very
very short period of time and of course
coinciding with uh you know lower sperm
count uh uh you know on the female side
this is just as big of a problem where
they're they're you know entering into
menration earlier uh they're suffering
from more PCOS and endometriosis
um you know of course we're seeing male
prostate cancer constantly on the rise
so I I you know I have been a big
advocate of okay we're we're in a dire
position right now I don't think we have
to be uh ashamed about that or or hide
from that fact. Uh but more importantly,
I also think this is to some degree in
relationship to our mental and physical
health
deterioration. And so in my opinion, if
there are obvious at least obvious
enough factors like endocrine disrupting
chemicals that are pervasive in every
single part of the world at this point,
we're seeing these declining levels and
hormones. We've measured them. We can
speak to them. I don't understand why we
wouldn't start with something like
testosterone replacement therapy over an
SSRI for example, which again in in the
research we're we're seeing SSRIs as
being a a essentially like we don't
understand why we're giving them. Uh and
and and whereas with testosterone we
have a very very clear understanding of
it, much clearer. Um and at the very
least uh god forbid the guy's still sad,
at least he's stronger uh and less fat
and maybe his wiener works a little bit
better. So, I'm just a I'm a big fan of
looking at that and same for the
females. I think that there's a huge
disparaging uh uh you know issue with
with female patients and on that same
level. Um and and some of the endocrine
disrupting chemicals again uh you know
even even so far as some of them
affecting our cortisol too uh where
we're seeing more cortisol on the rise
which is more catabolic. So it's
stripping muscle tissue um you know it's
it's it's stripping away our immune
system in a lot of ways. It's just a
really bad place to be and I I think
it's annoying that hormones aren't at
the forefront in a lot of ways just yet
and I think we're changing that. Yeah.
And what do you recommend patients to do
to protect themselves from EDCs or is
just getting on hormone replacement
immediately um a protection already?
Yeah, I that's a fantastic question. I I
think both really. I do think both. Um,
and I know that sounds probably a little
bit premature in some ways to some
people, but I I think I think the
silliest thing to do is start hormones
at the very latest point. I I think that
was the old school mentality, which was
uh, you know, we wait till a male or
female's uh, you know, uh, uh, bones
start to deteriorate and their muscle
tissue goes to and their brain
health is gone and then we can start
them on just a little bit of some sort
of synthetic hormone that's going to
kill them earlier anyways. versus why
don't we start at the the earliest point
we can frankly um if it's necessary and
if it's needed I think it should be
initiated uh the more we can preserve
muscle mass the more we can preserve
your bones the more we can preserve your
brain and your heart health uh it puts
less burden on the system at large it
puts less burden on your you know kind
of micro system at home I I think that's
fantastic as far as the endocrine
disrupting chemical side of things go I
I think it's extremely important to just
be mindful and at least aware. Um, you
know, you there's no sense in driving
yourself crazy trying to avoid it
because we can't. Um, but, you know,
don't microwave your food in plastic
Tupperware. Uh, try not to, you know,
wear plastic clothing all day long if
especially if you don't have to. Um,
attempt to, uh, you know, get outside
and get some sunlight. All the all the
basic tenants, right? Um, just try to
try to be mindful. uh try not to drive
yourself crazy and do your part there.
Um but again, I I do I'm an optimistic
guy. I do actually see at least in the
United States, you know, we've had some
really interesting changes going on over
the last few months. Um and and
hopefully we'll start seeing from more
of a top down approach a really big
shift. Yeah, let's uh certainly hope so.
Um do you also see a problem with the
the eating of soy and the soy and all
kinds of nutrition? Yeah, I I do. Um,
you know, I I think well, you know, soy
products at this point are almost like
wheat products. Um, meaning meaning I I
think probably there was a point in time
where soy wasn't so unbelievably
detrimental. Uh, and maybe similar to
wheat and at least especially what we've
done to it in the United States is just,
you know, bastardized these poor
products to the nth degree, uh, with,
you know, genetic engineering and things
of that nature. Um, and and uh we've
we've created a Frankenstein product and
and I'm somewhat curious if that is also
just potentiating some of the estrogenic
effects of something like soy for
example. Um, so, you know, again, I'm
not disparaging people from eating soy
at all, but or or you know, entertaining
that, but it is something that I would
not make a huge part of my diet. You
know, I agree with also like some of the
processed oils. um at least in my
opinion it seems very obvious that uh
eating too much of them is probably
somewhat detrimental to your overall
health. Um so yeah I hope that answer
your question Stephen. Yeah even in my
practice I see a lot of um moms with
their little kids sons often and yeah
they they switched completely from dairy
to soy products because of yeah
so-called or whatever. So a lot of young
boys are on soy instead of milk. I I
think that's frightening for the future.
Right. I couldn't agree more and it's
funny you mentioned that um you know a
lot of people have said you know Nico
you know what what are the natural
things I can do and and I always try to
remind people too you know sometimes
just because something's natural also
doesn't mean it's safe so uh you know I
I've spoken to a lot of my patients are
very health consscious and and and
that's wonderful and they they like the
some of the holistic and alternative
remedies um but for example I think you
know this being in your world of
skincare uh tea tree oil um lavender
oil. These essential oils are highly
highly highly estrogenic compounds. Um,
again, sparingly, totally fine and and
they have some amazing benefits. Um, but
used daily uh and frequently, it can it
can create some really I actually had a
male patient with gynecomastia and I'm
quite certain it was because he used an
incredible amount of tea tree oil for
acne. um like an unbeliev unsafe amount
of tea tree oil.